hello everybody
thanks for tuning in i'm uh really
pleased
to offer this video with katnie courtney
so i'll give some context for who she is
in this conversation in a second
um for some housekeeping so maybe you've
noticed but i've started to
uh be a little bit more active on my
channel as of late
now that i've completed my um the
writing that i did
on internet outer dialogues so i i'm
gonna start i have a bunch
more um things planned for the channel
so keep your eyes open for that
and
circling institute uh if you're
interested in
in in checking out what we're doing in
my company the circling institute
um the link is below we have uh
something open to everybody every
thursday night that's 6 p.m pacific
standard time
um the link for that's below
we also have a weekend coming up uh an
immersion circling weekend
so if you're interested in that the link
is below i think that's in a couple of
weeks
and i'll keep you posted on things that
are available also if you're interested
in doing one-on-one coaching with me
my my emails below and you can
let me know you're interested in that
and we can talk about that
all right i think that's all the
housekeeping for now
so kathy is she's really special to me
so kathy's one i consider one of my best
friends
um just to i just feel deeply bonded
with with kathy she's
um we have led together we've led
circling courses together
um we've like led a whole year-long
training together
and uh she's
and i think you'll see there's a
particular quality of openness to her
that um that is is it's quite unusual
right and and yet at the same time an
interest
in um moving into the
into into the areas that maybe are the
most uncomfortable
yet where a lot of truth lies
um she's quite she is quite
industrious i would say and she actually
with she's got a couple of kids she's a
single mom
and she um couldn't she wanted to learn
how to do circling
and she couldn't do the trip because we
were doing all this stuff
in uh in person at that time
and so she couldn't fly out to
california but she really wanted to
learn how to do it and so she
we did a whole thing in in um
in north carolina and she
we started a whole program out there and
that was really through her
um her clarity and her industriousness
um so she's she's pretty special
this conversation we talk about her work
on in the work that she's doing with
with couples and what she's learning
uh she's uh talking about different
models
of places that she's coming from in
relationship and that really opened up
the conversation to talk about
um what it is
what is it that what is it that takes
place
in moments of deep connection
and intimacy
that transcends transcends
just the you could say the benefits or
the outcome of that relationship but
there's something
we discuss what is it about intimacy
that's transcendent not in just the
experience of intimacy which can be
transcended but transcends
um the impact of what it takes to be
intimate on
the rest of our lives and so we spend a
lot of time really exploring that
and we end up talking a lot about her
relationship with her daughters
and what you know how how that works out
in
in being a parent and all the
complexities
they come up with with that and those
relationships and how she works with
people
um really enjoyed the conversation with
her
and i've been wanting to have her on for
a long time because she's just
she's just a neat person and i think has
a lot to offer
so um i if you're interested in
contacting kathy and i definitely would
recommend that if if you
if you want to find a work with
your relationship uh she's great for
that um
one-on-one coaching all that but the
link for her
her website is below and
enjoy thank you for tuning in
gotta have something absolutely
so we just so everybody welcome to kathy
this is mostly what it was about is i
just wanted to welcome people to captain
and uh and uh
it's it's great seeing you on my on my
screen
and it's good to be free and we were
just talking about we just started
getting into it
but what one of the things is is you you
and i have worked together
in circling right we did a whole a whole
thing in asheville
for for a whole like a whole year and
then some um and then we just became
really good friends
and uh and now you're doing we were just
talking about
um the coaching work that you're doing
with working with couples and you
actually have been doing some other
training
and and what have you been like so who
who were you just talking about what was
the thing that you were just talking
about
talking about like yeah of a map yes
well thanks so much i'm so happy to be
here with you too guy
it's always um good to be with you
and um yeah i was talking about how
i have been you know as guy said
talking teaching and working with
circling as a framework which will is
always kind of like a first
love in a sense for me it's um
just such a deep practice of being with
each other and being with the moment
and um and i've been working with
couples and i
relationship has really just always been
a driving
force for me to understand to shift
to have freedom to find intimacy
and and um so i recently
started training with a particular type
of therapy called it's called real
sorry relational life therapy and the
the founder of this work the teacher of
this work his name is terry real
and he has been a practicing
relational therapist for over 30 years
and
he like his main um
sort of concept is
we're we're living within the system of
patriarchy
and there's there's most often in most
relationships
it doesn't matter if they're
heterosexual or not
you know but in most relationships
there's
one person and this is when things get
tough one person is one
up and one person is one down
so he describes it as basically
they're both it's on a continuum
of if you look at self-esteem so the one
up is usually the grandiose person
that's shameless
you know like their coping strategy has
been
to feel better than others you know they
they typically as children they were
given an
uh like a grandiose sense of themselves
um
and then the one down is typically the
one
riddled with shame that you know has a
low sense of self-worth
and so in his work he's got a very clear
map of
how to first empower the latent or the
one down person
and then how to he calls joining in the
truth
with the one-up person so and
and what i love about his work is
he's completely agenda-less
i mean i shouldn't say a genderless but
not attached to any outcome right
right and in the seat of the therapist
um you really practice i mean
you're in relation to so it's all
like moment to moment very you're very
relational you reveal yourself
um you come from the sort of knowing
that everybody has this um
possibility for relational health
right um
and so he's got this really beautiful
way of coming from love and compassion
non-attachment but
really does call people out
in the truth and you see you can see
physiologically that things really shift
in the moment very dramatically so
that's what i like about it it's this
great map
but it's also very effective um
and so because you know i think sorry go
ahead
it's a good yeah go ahead yeah
well i was gonna say you know i've
myself over the years been in different
relational
like relationship therapy
[Music]
and it's not all been very effective
because
it's a lot of like back and forth and
back and forth
and um you know maybe you get to
understand your partner a little better
but i personally
haven't necessarily been in relationship
therapy that's
created actual like actual
change right like yeah
yeah um so
this seems to be very effective and i'm
i am
i'm excited because as a circler or a
circling
teacher facilitator i can bring a lot of
the qualities of circling of presence
um being with what is
paying attention to what's alive right
you know um encircling you know we call
the
stage of the warrior where we speak to
dissonance
but we've already created attunement and
safety and trust
yeah so you know a lot of those
different things
yeah in the and you said something
really interesting
you said it's basically what it what it
sounds like it's like what
the thing that you're getting trained in
right now is
he's got a structure where he's got some
he's got some like ways of seeing
typical power dynamics that happen
right and can't approach those things
um and it seems like it seems like i
think i heard you say it's like
when you've been in therapy couples
therapy
even though you understand the person
better
it doesn't necessarily it doesn't
necessarily effective
right there's something about
what do you think you're seeing right
right now that's like what's the
difference that makes it effective or
not
yes so
in this map he uses leverage so for
instance
say you have somebody that um is being
verbally abusive that's kind of extreme
but oftentimes when somebody is verbally
abusive
they're coming from their adaptive child
you know so
basically from the ages of 5 to
17 the ways we've adapted to our
circumstances and our own childhood
trauma and whatnot you know and
most people seem to be still living from
this adaptive child in fact it's it's
really supported in our society i mean
look who's running our country he's like
a really
adaptive child um
so the idea is is that
he he works to like gain
leverage so basically i've heard him say
to this one guy there was this uh model
um
you know they were doing a demo
basically
and he said i've got good news and bad
news which do you want to hear first
and he was like you're okay
the bad news is you're verbally abusive
to your wife
and if you don't turn that around you're
gonna lose her
you're going to lose her is that is that
what you want you know
so he first finds the leverage
yeah and so he joins people in the truth
but then he's got this leverage of like
you are going to lose your relationship
because he's already empowered the wife
in this case to say that she's at her
end like she's about to walk out the
door
right so you know if if you want her to
walk out the door
that's fine keep being verbally abusive
but if you if you don't want that yeah
then
he gets a contract from them right there
like
the good news is i think you're a good
person and we can really
we can we can really make a change here
like i know that you're capable of
of stopping these behaviors are you on
board
and sometimes you'll like lean in and
shake their hand when they say yes
you know like he gets a contract from
them in that moment
[Music]
so that's kind of how he will do it but
then he's got other steps of like
how eventually after he goes through
this education
phase with the couple he then makes sure
that they create a support system in
their
in their community right
so so that's just that's some of the
ways
interesting yeah what what do you think
about that
it makes sense especially because
well one is it is it sounds it sounds
like
that that leverage piece right is
exactly what that person
doesn't have in the moments of the
argument
right because you're making a
distinction because usually the person
you know there's truth to whatever the
argument is right that's why
it usually doesn't work out it doesn't
usually just work with couples when
they're an argument
to work out the content right
it's not really that's not where the
relationship is right
and so it sounds like in the moments
where he
like the husband will be verbally
abusive if he can say hey
when you weren't feeling like this you
said this
right and this is the thing that matters
to you
right do you really want to like keep
doing that
right and it reminds reminds them and
it seems like i could imagine from the
husband's perspective you can give them
leverage
to like put their attention somewhere
else so to look at something else or be
open to something else
while their defenses are so up right
yeah right yeah
and then i mean he'll go into early
childhood work you know
so basically in that next moment he said
who
who did this to you when you're a kid
and it came out that it was his
stepmother so he then he said
you know every time you speak to your
wife
like this you're choosing your
stepmother over your relationship
do you have a photograph like he like he
took it to the step of like
when you feel that way pull out the
photograph and tell your stepmother
right now i'm going to choose you over
my wife
you know like these very sort of
pragmatic
tools of how to come into reality with
what you're really doing
in that moment right you know this is
like i can say so i'm in
the beginning of this map i'm finding it
very interesting i'm now learning about
the relational brain
and what exactly is happening moment to
moment
in a therapy context of yeah you know
in the there in the coaches seat the
therapist seat
and really foster a sense of safety how
to recognize when somebody is in their
like their neocortical brain or the
subcortical brain
what's kind of happening moment to
moment on a physiological level
so it's just it's super fascinating i i
um
i love it so i can
geek out on it all day right and you're
you're i would imagine is this one of
the things that you're finding out with
the with the neurological stuff
of like where you you've actually
already been related to somebody when
they're
you can like on a subcortical level
versus
like a ideocortex level like
you've already been on some level
intuitively
sensing that and responding accordingly
and now you're learning about like oh
this there's actually something there
right that you could measure yes
and what's exciting to me guy is
if i could just say a little bit and
please i'm no expert so i
just want to like make that clear this
is
i'm just beginning i mean i when i was
in my 20s
i took anatomy physiology multiple times
because i just loved it so much
and i've i've had a long hiatus of
studying
about the brain or about the body and so
i have a fascination with it but i don't
know a whole lot but what i do
understand
is the subcortical brain
which includes different aspects of the
sub of the subcortical brain
basically makes a decision in 1 8 of a
second
so if i'm in if something comes toward
me
so say say my partner or somebody i love
says something to me and my subcortical
brain is saying this is a threat yep
if i will respond if i don't have
integration with my neocortical brain
to calm my subcortical brain then i will
respond from a very reactive fight
you know fight flight freeze that kind
of stuff
and um and then i'll have no access to
my adult
my adult self yeah so
the key is it's not that that doesn't
stop happening
in contrast your neocortical brain
is a much slower processing aspect of
your brain
and it makes a decision i think it's
like two to three seconds
versus an eighth of a second so if i get
that
same uh stimulus that created a
an affect from my
particle brain the the part of my
neocortex
can calm it and make
and make a sort of wise adult
decision in response and that's the
that's when the brain is integrated
and you're creating new pathways as you
learn to integrate the brain more
it actually also reminds me of like you
know
i don't know a whole lot about
attachment theory but i think
it would be like what would feel more
like
your nervous system is more sued there's
more sick like of a secure bond
and whatnot but what i want to get to is
i think
that encircling over time
that's what's happening on a brain on a
brain level
is that we're learning to integrate
those different aspects
aspects of the brain so that the kind of
more adult
self can and soothe
the part that's feeling wounded and
reactive
yeah yeah and then more effective
like stay in the moment present and
relational
right it's interesting because it that
makes sense
especially if i bring in another thing
that you just said
where you know here's bob who's like
you know right and justified
and maybe is even correct in what he's
saying
right and then he starts yelling
and then the therapist is there you're
sitting there like hey
you remember right some love
it gives him hit like it gives him
leverage
to be like okay like
deal with this impulse right and
like stop and like actually look right
because it
because it does seem like the one of the
big things i've often thought about the
brain
you know looking at things from a brain
perspective
like the macula seems
i think it's talked about the the
amygdala gives you
like a warning right
and i think that if you have like
perhaps like a lot of trauma
right where the warning it gave you
right um
was true on some level right but partial
and that it but if the if the warning or
your
freakout when you were a kid never got
responded to as you're freaking out
let's like check out reality and see if
you are
right if you for example if the people
who were supposed to help you like check
out reality were the ones hurting you
right yeah you never really get to
because i think the amygdala knows all
those subcortical regions are actually
not giving you statements
about this is it's dangerous
i think it's supposed to say ask you a
question
is this dangerous right
right and so just getting to the getting
to the point where you can
you can actually feel that and then have
it be a question
that you then engage right the neocortex
to actually look is that well maybe it
is dangerous maybe it's not just
that little frame seems like a
big difference to me yeah
feels like a big difference i think
we in my experience i think
in the practice of circling
that's something that we develop
yeah would you say yeah
well i think it's especially
because a lot because i would say if you
look at the structure of circling it has
a lot to do with being in someone's
attention
right and being honest about what's
happening
but also being visible in your attention
and all the different things that can
happen when you pay attention to me
are also all the things that that is one
of the things i've always said about
this is what makes connections so
interesting
it's interesting there's a good way of
putting it right it's like i
like you could say something to me that
can reveal a truth
about my life that'll change everything
right like we opened we're so
radically open to each to each other
right
that you can make sounds with your face
point them in my direction
right and i i can hear them i can even
hear it wrongly
have it reveal something true about me
that is
it's there's a radical openness that we
have to each other
right which is
so anything yeah it's circling really is
about
doing that consciously on purpose
and being with the pos just the thing
that's like
tolerating the possibilities within that
inner subjective
kind of space that's a lot to deal with
if you ask me jeez i know
this over here as you're saying that um
like a burning inside of me which
occurs like um just the weight of
responsibility
being human and using words in the face
of another human that has
anything to do with them
even if we're like fully owning our
experience you know one of my
i notice i'm very sensitive to when
people make assertions they make
truths about me or about others
that feel like
those have a lot of power but they may
not be accurate and they're not owning
that
that's their experience i i feel like
that can have a very
a strong impact on others you know
the words we say have such impact on
others such that
it can actually change the course of
one's life
if depend depending on their level of
openness right because
not all of us have certainly
not everybody walks around as open as
you and i
like i think we we both noticed
a while back when we did that jordan
peterson um personality
test
and my level of my i was my percentile
of openness was something ridiculous
like
98 like i was in the 98th percentile
yeah we
portion exclamation that came up against
it
like so not everybody is
as is as open
um as you and i may be but
still even so we have
such uh there's such
possibility for deep impact
on one another deep impact
and what i'm also hearing is
and also there's there's the whole
element of like the
that we could have deep impact on each
other
and i could even have the intention to
have
a particular impact on you right
and it ends up you can mishear me
right however we're telling you
i think i've told you this when my dad
had this story where
he's he's been he's been sober in a for
you know a billion years and uh somebody
came up to him in a meeting
and apparently he used to sponsor him
and
they had lost touch with each other and
he comes up to my dad and he's like oh
my god
this thing you said to me i haven't been
able to like reach you since but like
it has changed my life i never it's this
whole thing where it like it changed his
entire life his relationship with his
kids are better and then
he moved and all this kind of stuff
and he's like i got i just have to thank
you and oh and then like
then he walks away and my dad was like
he misheard what i said
oh my god like that is
hilarious and you have to kind of just
chalk it off to like
he heard what he needed to hear exactly
exactly i guess there's a certain amount
of
needing to let go and trust
that right you know
people will take what they need let go
of what they don't
yeah and so the way in which to be open
you know
it's uh there's if you
look at all of the possibility that
you're open to when you open up to
another person
right like there's a sense in which it's
not even like a direct causal
relationship
right where i say i say something to you
and like
you may hear it really accurately but
then i actually
i actually didn't understand what i said
to you i didn't understand it
right it's so it's not a direct causal
thing but there's a
but especially i would say
like a little bit outside of a like a
psychological viewpoint
like on uh one of the things i've
appreciated about right doing this
paper that i wrote right this chapter
right on dot
on via logos is just
really getting that
what we call the word right when i say
the world
when i say like my guy's life and guy's
world and i we talk about the world
right this kind of horizon
right that everything that i call
anything is somehow in
this world of intelligibility
and it's and we say okay 1800s it was a
different world
right 2004
the world we're in right there's a
different world
well how what is that world and how does
it change and what is that difference
and when you really look at that what
you realize is that the world
unfolds as intelligibility via
discourse right like how does the how
does the wisdom or lack of wisdom of a
culture or how does a tradition
continue to unfold over time or change
over time and
what is the medium upon which it does
that right well it's the medium of
basically the way things go up as
intelligible
well how does that how does that go on
it's through conversation
right it's through interaction
like it's through discourse so
i think writing that really had me get i
think a deep
well first i started understanding more
about like well why
why is my attention so much going into
relationship
right but i think i got more of a hit of
like well
it seems like if you're going to look at
if you're going to look if you're going
to if you're going to change anything
right the changing of such will have the
biggest difference
it seems that if it seems that if you
change
the structure of the way people
communicate with one another
you will in fact change the world right
and here's and i say that with some i i
personally say that with some
with humility because i don't even know
i don't even know it's not like
the change in the structure of the
relationship that i think
will make a big difference could
actually just everything up
and i you wouldn't find out until like
five traditions after i die
right you look at karl marx i think he
may
i don't know what mark should say about
what happened with communism but
but but just the sense of
the the awareness of discourse
yeah and then and then you look at our
time
and the way social media is really
dramatically
changed the structure of the way that we
discourse
right we have that it really has
you know what's coming up for me and
hearing you is uh
it's a it's this fine line because if
you
okay let me see if i can form this
thought it's just coming to me
like you're saying it's like it's
arising in me in this moment and i don't
quite know the words yet so i'm going to
give it a shot
but if i hold a particular
view and let's say
maybe it's kind of a rigid view because
let's just from a personal standpoint i
came from an extremely rigid
paradigm yeah and so
in a rigid paradigm which can look
different ways for different you know
rigid belief system rigid culture rigid
anything
where you came from south africa right
where you came from
okay so like think you know
british post-colonial
very much into you know politeness
how you're perceived right way wrong way
so on so forth so
if the discourse remains
in that context
there's this very limited
you're just basically perpetuating that
context
or that paradigm right
and so what i'm
struck by in our conversation is
there's this fine line between
[Music]
uh driving discourse or like
coming from a particular place and then
surrendering and letting go and
staying open that
allows or disallows
uh creativity newness
uh yeah shifting
new paradigms new contacts created
um and i find myself actually now that
we're talking about it i find myself
playing with that yeah
quite a bit when i'm talking to people
um
there's a sense of i know my context i
know my background
influences let's say
i'm very weary of them on one hand
but i still know that they're the you
know
they create the they're still in the
background and the
fabric of me or something so i'm weary
of them
but there's also a thing like
what am i trying to say i'm weary of
them
i notice i don't want them to influence
what is revealed
part of it is me part is not
i also have things that i do believe in
or that
do feel strong but i'm also very much uh
committed and value something
new yeah
are you from totally yeah
yeah i feel extremely invested in
what is wanting to reveal itself
yet i feel limited by my background
and where i currently
find myself on my own frontier of like
what i
what i can let go of what i can
hold what i can participate in
yeah and so there you're basically i
think what i'm hearing you say
is europe
you you started off by saying i think
what you're saying is
yeah not so much it's not i want to
drive something forward with
relationship
right and make something
so but you said no i really wanna i
wanna but i wanna open
to something being possible right
and that sometimes this background that
i don't i
i'm suspect of a lot because it's you
know
it's like i'm this big and it's this big
and that causes problems
all right yeah so there's a
there's a but you want to open to
something something relationally
you want to be open to something that
you can't foresee
but you do but you are present enough
to that something is possible right that
you can open to it because it's an
interesting question it's like what am i
open to if i'm open to
what i don't know yet which is
which i think is precisely i mean i mean
i really this is where i hear
at least my own personal experience with
leading circles
that's the sensibility of circling
precisely in that your
i think it's one of the things that is
is the skill if you want to call it that
which is an attunement to something new
emerging
right basically it's attuning to
something new emerging
that where you sense a sense of moreness
or an
intelligibility that's that gathers and
you can open to it and welcome it and
like
invite it forward right
yeah yeah yeah and
i you know we're talking we're kind of
going really
matter but when we bring it back to
relationship
um what does that mean you know and it
means
you know if i think about my daily life
and who i'm relating to
you know i've got the the clients that i
work with i have the
you know folks coming to me for circling
but then i have my relationship
and i have my daughters and i have my
family
and i have my friends you know and
what i'm really interested in is how to
how to let me see if i can put this in
woods like
how to continue to engage in these
sorts of you use the word discourse
how to bring language and stay fresh and
alive
to even what's wanting to emerge that's
new
with my daughters with my you know
partner
i think it's probably hardest with my
kids
because i don't know about you guy
but you know you're constantly having to
catch up
in a way to where your child is like a
a new seeing you know you you just think
you get
to to make sense of who they are in the
world
and and like you you adjust you know to
that
to that new like the meaning we make or
the sense
the sense making that we make about our
children and then they change again
yeah yeah and
on some level you know i'm responsible
for
parenting them which i'm still trying to
figure out what the that means
but you know and to stay
like to continue to to um
stretch myself to stay present to what
is
now and now and now and it seems to be
constantly changing
right i well
just when i was getting used to his
bleach pink hair
he had bleached pink that's awesome then
became this thing where i was like wait
a minute did you
get braces what's and he has
underneath his lips that
i keep thinking oh he got braces and
then it's this thing it's like an
earring
yeah oh appears piercing
is that is that a little bit like what
you mean is like they're
what they're really
yeah or like i'm trying to make sense of
the fact that my
daughter who's like super liberal and
you know headstrong and all this stuff
decided
to get a job at duncan duncan donuts
and having this whole experience
of what it's like to be amongst
people that she has never experienced
before
i live in like these people are like
country no offense to anybody but they
like
they've grown up with like serious
trauma none of them have gone to
college there's like many different
family members all working in the same
shift
and most of them are extremely
like but right-wing is
finding super like she's
super energized about getting to
understand
the other side like this whole
population of people that she's
never been exposed to before and somehow
it makes me miss your daughter oh she's
so freaking awesome
she's awesome and she's really like
having these
mind-blowing experiences and really
loving
working at this silly drive-through
like dunkin donuts like seeing
a part of society that she's never been
exposed to before
so that's a different aside but i think
for me like
yeah you know continuing to stay
fresh and open and like
you know agile and like where am i
holding tight where am i
where am i not like hearing where am i
um attaching you know so what is it like
what is it like having your daughter
work at dunkin donuts
kind of shocked at first i almost found
myself wanting to steer her away from
that you know like
what are you doing really like seriously
um but
so i didn't say any of that because i
noticed that was those are all my
assumptions and judgments yeah well it
sounds like it
sounds like just that right there what
i'm hearing is like
just that wanting to say it but choosing
not to say that
and wait i just got this sentence like
waiting
being like okay well let's open up to
that
i'll i'll keep my judgments to myself
and open
to what she's up to
is that one way that you kind of catch
up to what she's looking at and what
where she's seeing
and as a parent
yeah yeah that right there to me
i think that's kind of rare
like i think that's pretty rare
like one is just to have the distinction
that the things that are coming up for
you
are things in you
it's not necessarily the world right
i think just having that kind of
discernment between my judgments about
things and
the way things actually are to have that
space
especially when you have a visceral
because i don't think there's any
there's any way of getting around like
the biological species
in a way for like being like being a
mother especially i think the kind of
like hormonal nervous system orientation
like
keep her safe right is just
you've got billions of years cooking
through you with that one
on some level those judgments probably
are in relationship
to protecting her and then pausing
and then keeping them to yourself on
purpose
and then seeing what happens i think
that's pretty rad
yeah yeah
maybe so maybe so i mean i think
the gift that i'm seeing in it is
what is showing instead being that i've
paused and like held back and waited
i'm getting the gift of seeing my kids
see
these really big things through her own
eyes and her own experience and she's
looking at capitalism and she's looking
at
the food industry and she's looking at
like
mom i don't see how people
can work really really hard
paid get paid minimum wage and have to
live in a trailer
something about that feels extremely off
to me
well i didn't tell her that you know but
she's
because i held back she's getting this
vis
she's getting a visceral experience
of the injustice of that
right right and she's teaching
me and and i'm seeing her and like it's
just
it's really ends up being such a gift
yeah yeah
yeah and i think
what that brings up for me guy is
i mean like you said as a mom the
protection
hormones and the biology
and the genetics and just the ancestral
just all of the
urges within myself and in
mothers and parents in general
it's it's such a basic instinct to
override but i see
too like i work with a mother and a
daughter and i work with them
separately and what i'm
seeing is there is such
such intelligence in
like in these young kids there there's
this intelligence that's
that's inherent that if you give it
space
it actually has its own
its own unfolding yeah and
the process of trying to put it in a box
which is common that's what we want to
do as parents because it feels like
safety there's security there's
you know something known in a sense
but if you actually like
challenge yourself to see the box
and step outside the box
and allow some of the intelligibility to
unfold
yeah whoa then
then it's more than you can imagine it's
more than you can control it's more than
you can manage it's more than you can
predict
yeah and i believe that's true for all
relationships in a sense but it feels
most strong
in the dynamic for me with my daughters
and
right wow
that's i think it's really
causing and the in in this case
it's like watching her start to have
like like to actually think about what
she's seeing
right so she's taking this initiative
what she wants to move towards something
that she's not familiar with
and then she starts to see they're like
the facts as they unfold and then she
has these questions
about this seems unjust
right like like where is the exactly the
injustice of this is just something
seems bad about like
having to do this if you have to do this
right and so you're
that way you made is like her her
responding to the world
on her own in that way yeah
yeah yeah yeah and i think we
often in our need to
control
and i'll say as parents but this happens
in all relating
you know there's a certain unknown
entity
and we it feels unsafe and so we try to
control
but but what we end up doing is
like really
losing out on the benefits of the
intelligibility of something
you know that that it has like this life
that's
you know has a time and has an opening
and has a
movement yeah yeah
totally which
when you're in the presence of that and
you actually witness
that i think i can safely say
that you you too appreciate that
with a lot of depth like to be a witness
to
the unfolding of anybody
right it's like well it's like
witnessing a miracle isn't it
yeah like that
it's interesting because looking at
like when i've looked at having kids
again and stuff right that
you know what are you really deciding
when you just have a kid
if you really look
you're basically deciding you're just
you're making a choice to be open to
like giving birth to meaning
it's like you're looking meaning itself
right
right and you're looking at meaning that
on some level that thing that you just
talked about parenting is this
this strange place where through the
course of the time
you want to leave them as open as
possible to the world
and as safe as possible at the world and
deal with your own psychology in the
face of that
in finding balance well why would you
even do that well it's because
on some level you have something in
front of you that is like
priceless in preciousness
right is you have to tell it somebody
who's
free who's
the meaning itself is what you're
basically looking at when i think when
you look at another human being
so to give birth to that right the
humongous responsibility
so much suffering what else would you
want to do
right you're basically
signing up for some of life's
deepest suffering fear
you know heartache but also
it it's there's something more
valuable and worthy that has it so that
has you
signing up for that yeah yeah
i could totally see her by the way i
could totally see her like
making a choice to work like to work
there and to like observe all that even
for
that sake wanting to and then be she's
so cool
you're super cool yeah yeah
yeah so i'm wondering about like how to
translate that
to actual like intimate relationships
because
i think there too
what happens i i don't again
i don't really know what i'm going to
say but there's something very important
that can be learned
around this stuff in intimate
relationships that i think
then have an impact on the world around
us
yeah what what do you what do you sense
about them
okay well look if we go back to leverage
everybody
you know
what i imagine is so when relationships
are not working
um there's a lot of suffering around
that
and you know there's lots of reasons why
relationships don't work
but there's a lot of things that we get
caught in like being able to listen
getting somebody else's perspective
you know gaining more um
trust and safety secure attachment
bonding
just all those different things once we
have
have if we really put effort in
being better listeners better partners
being more flexible open a
willingness to continue to
look outside the box a willingness to
continue
to open a willingness to
get curious about somebody else you know
and
really and these skills and capacities
that we have to grow
to be better in relationship like
you end up doing it everywhere yeah
yeah but i mean that's that that's my
thought
so like right it has a lot of meaning
in relationship there's a lot of value
and
weight in in creating joy in your life
having good relationships
but then you become a changed person
that then
affects how you treat your neighbor or
how you
you know show up in your community
so you're saying like that there's
something about like
there's the part on the level of like
okay if we get better at relating to
our family and the people
and our friends that just improving that
alone is gonna like obviously shift the
quality of your life but
you're bringing in something else here
you're basically saying like
no there's something that happens
through
being a better communicator through
having more intimacy through being more
open to your kids
and finding that balance and working
through your stuff
that when you're there's something that
happens to you to
one through what it takes to be good at
those things
right such that when you're walking
around in the world
something happens there that you that
you carry
yeah what do you think what do you think
that is
i'm enjoying tracking you the movement
of your
body heart insightful mind
i'm enjoying it too because i i feel
like i'm a little all over the place so
i'm really grateful for you kind of
honing it in
and yeah um
we didn't really have a strong plan for
this conversation and
you know it's just it feels good to kind
of meander but i think there's a general
something that that we're touching on
would you agree yeah i'm i'm actually
following
the movement of the conversation and
actually where you're
where your mind's going right now what's
occurring for you
right because you're basic
yeah basically i'm hearing you say is
like you're tracking one level
you're doing this work with couples
right
and and then there's another part where
it's like well i'm
in why am i interested in that even in
the first place
right and there's something
there's something that happens through
that right that has a
has a more meta or a bigger picture that
has implications for that
yeah it feels like the the talos of
this conversation yeah
so recently i i recognized and this is
not the first time i've recognized this
but it was i
re um visited
the thing that really hurts me the most
is when i hear lack of understanding
between people
and the amount of pain and suffering
that can happen
just by misunderstanding or not getting
or not taking the time to
creates enormous suffering in the world
enormous i mean
i that's that's what i see like you know
even
if you take it to
like some injustices that are happening
in the world
or way p ways people are speaking about
the
other or ways that they see them and
make assumptions and there's something
about that for me i can remember
since i was a kid that when i heard
other people talk about
either groups of people or
individuals i
always like felt pain around like
that person not being understood and
there has to be
a deeper like a deep and a deeper
um context to why
these things are occurring that are
creating dissonance
suffering all that kind of stuff
so that's just like the in the
background for me that's a driving force
and that always has been to like
create more compassion and understanding
and stuff like that
yeah but
being in relationship
whether it's intimate or
like a sexually intimate relationship or
intimate with a child
or a mother or whatever um
really drives us
to
to look at like to look at ourselves but
that's not
quite that's not quite the right words
but like
um to create more
to create more intimacy we
have to like it feels like by the nature
of who we are we
have to transcend ourselves yeah
there it is yeah light bulbs went off
for me
yeah yeah
i mean we can choose to not and then we
have a certain
like level of life you know that's like
blah and some people do that and that's
fine you know
people can get to do that but if you
want more and if you
want if you want aliveness in your life
if you want joy if you want depth if you
want
passion if you want creativity if you
want more
you have to transcend yourself and your
circumstances
and your psyche and your you know you
have to
so in the process of doing that
as i transcend myself
um i'm also
inherently changing the way i relate to
life
and everything that's included in life
yeah yeah so there's something about
so what i just heard there
i could see actually let's see if i
didn't hear it
what it takes to be intimate with the
people in my life
right it's not what i heard you say is
it's impossible to be
intimate and we and in this case we're
talking about
especially when i don't understand to
actually understand
right um and even
even if i don't agree with what i'm
understanding open to you as such
right to understand you that there's
some there's a
the machinery i use for that right is
the same
it's it's the transcendent machinery
right
intimacy is a form of transcendence
yeah and that there's
well like when you talk about like and
that's a that's a non-local occurrence
by definition you're
you're transcending what's local or the
particular problem or argument or the
content
of it and you're going deep into it and
then somehow
seeing more feeling more experiencing
more
through it and that that
that that there's something about the
there's the muscles that that works
just like when you're done maybe i often
think about when you're done with the
yoga class
right when you're not thinking about
yoga walking down the street you're just
more balanced and open
in your body about
what it takes to be intimate that is
also what it takes to be with the world
as such
right that there's uh that that openness
translates into being open
in multiple contexts in ways that are
probably hard to predict
yes and in order to be intimate
or to like grow in intimacy
ultimately it it requires
gaining some freedom from ourselves from
like you know from the binds that
have you know that
we've created this the binds that we've
created through life circumstances
growing up
you know so just by the nature of being
with another in that way
i have to move
through some of those binds some people
may call that trauma
we may call it strategy you know like
coping strategies
whatever it is the things that have kept
us safe
you you have to
be with them in a profound way and move
beyond them
in order to to really be in this
interdependent um
relational true relational field where
you and i are same as you're not better
i'm not worse
so on so forth we're in a more of an
interdependent
like flow state
but i have the more like i have to gain
freedom from some of the binds
that have not allowed that in the past
and so once i do
then i no longer look at you know
um
i no longer look at the same i i can no
longer look at the
world in the same way yeah
yeah yeah so that like that feels for me
like the bigger like the meta
drive for me is to help shift
help transcendence to help people
transcend through the vehicle our
relationship and
i feel um yeah that's just my place in
the world you know
yeah totally i love this i love the
i just i i love the thing that you're
talking about
um
i mean i share your intuition about it
sorry what else do you love about that
like how do you know you love that and
and what would you
say what would you say in your words
about it well
yeah it's i think one of the reasons i
think
you know for example people think that
like people oftentimes assume with me
that i like i really like people
i know data right and like uh that
i have i just must really like just like
people in general or something like that
and i don't think i like or don't like
people more than anybody else
um
with with circling i think what is shine
forth to me
isn't as a result of liking people it's
actually
what it takes to know somebody right
i have found to be deeply transcended
right
um and that
yeah the ability to to look at the world
and have the set like whatever it is
that's intelligible about it that's
beyond
the particular my particular frame of
reference
right it's that thing that has
it glow through that that
that is actually the thing that i love
right
and there's just nothing like
relationships that will just bring
in every ounce of like every way that
you don't want to do that
you know that's like what it's like
in the face of you not giving me
anything i want and
like i don't feel understood or whatever
like can i still open to you in a
particular way
right in the face of that can i still
see you not
beyond my own conceptions of you because
i think
there really is that that sense in which
i still i still don't know exactly
when i'm talking to you when i say i see
you i can't i don't really know what i'm
what i mean by you like
there it's very easy to
categorize people it's very easy and
oftentimes you should
like we live with eight billion people
right there's like all kinds of
reasons why like we have filters and
judgments and stuff like that is
they're not all negative right but when
i
when it matters and when i want to like
and i open up to you right and it
and it seems that there's a place where
when we open up to another
like another person you're
i it's basically there's this process of
like really
opening something beyond yeah
my conception of you my image of you
right
i'm opening up to i think
intelligibility itself
right a sense of of being this
um and something yeah
my own mind right that you can start to
access that
and that's that's like the reward from
that
is for me i think it's just like it has
me live with
i think i just become a better person
right
overall i think the world becomes a lot
more interesting place
i think
i think you have you end up there yeah
the response is
if i just like kind of look at my own
life the responses that i have from
other
people and the life that i've created
and all of that stuff
right seems to be opening up
possibilities in ways of life that are
i don't think would be there otherwise
yeah yeah
so i think i gotta be with your
sensibility
say that again in other words i'm
driving with your with your sensibility
around this
i think that's the reason that you and i
have
connected so deeply so quickly is that
we recognize
that some there's like a similar um
bias or not really a bias but just a
deep interest and desire
for that for that which you just spoke
of for
the the thing that's wanting to be
revealed
you know absolutely and that like
you know i find myself strangely
fascinated by dissonance and difficulty
yeah you know like i don't consider
myself a disharmonious kind of person
in fact i would like to i i was just
i'd sometimes like to find more of my
inner to be honest like
you know i'm soft by nature
yet i
i find myself moving toward
some of that like disruption
and i wouldn't say it's drama because i
i stay away from drama
for the most part but when when there's
that
tension or that disruption or that
moment before an opening or
is that you know is that the sign of
the thing emerging is that
one of the ways that you
do do you relate to that
like the i like the look on your face
that came over in that moment
no
i was like revealing a crush on somebody
or something
yeah i do i do love that kind of stuff
i do love that and i love watching it
being in the seat of coach and
watching some of the
uh like both the revealing and then the
some of the when when
when things start shedding from
like a couple i'm working with you know
the truth comes out like the truth gets
revealed
and then it's out there explicit
and then you watch like a little bit of
chaos a little bit of chaos a little bit
of discombobulation
you can almost see it in the entire body
of somebody
and then there's a moment of like
even if truth is difficult
there's there's this moment of breath
like like thank goodness
you know like we can all be in reality
in this moment we're all in
this present moment reality
and even if it's tough to see even if
it's
the thing i've been avoiding there's
like a
there's a relief there's a settling
there's a breath there's a freshness and
i love like i love that moment
i think that i think what you're
describing because i've seen you a
thousand times me
what about right like you know so soft
way basically ask
the most difficult question or point to
the most difficult thing
oh god is it that bad
it's that is that good right it's that
good i'd say
but yeah i think what i'm hearing you
say
is you essentially love the truth
but in the not not the truth that's
correct or right
but the truth that's revealed
yeah and in my experience
so far
i i noticed that others seem to like it
too
yeah yeah yeah
and i think even in the moment of
that truth becoming explicit
things start to i imagine like a cascade
of physiological events that occur
when that truth becomes explicit yeah
yeah you know what i mean like i don't
know exactly what's happening
neurologically in the body but i know
for me
something there's some sort of synergy
that's happening
on a physiological level and i imagine
in that moment there's a
like a re like a a shuffling of some
things like a
reorganizing of you know
physiology right
right i could i just sensed that and
it's the truth of
it's that sense of well
like i wrote a like a tweet today i
hardly ever tweet
but somebody was trying to oh my god
look at you when i was somebody who was
i i heard somebody talking about
tweeting and i was like
i had this thought and about thinking
and tweeting or something so i
wrote this tweet of um just today it's
like
is it me or does it seem like all the
good stuff
is hidden
oh my god that's true
but it's it's like
i think that's what i'm i think that's
your
i sense is like the thing that you're
like if you see
concealment if you see
some somebody's defenses or if you see
something
unsaid right that it's unsaid you're not
you're not um
why it's humorous what we're laughing at
right is that it look it may look like
you're just
into just discomfort but you're
but no it's like what the discomfort's
linked to and i think what you sense
right is that no like the good stuff is
actually that which is most enigmatic
it's the most concealed it has the it's
the most paradoxical
right and that if you just turn towards
the hard thing
right in other words it's like another
way of saying that is like
the most riches richest
existential ontological all those words
right revealing are
are it takes something
for that to disclose itself and that if
we attune to that
i think this is what you're saying is
that and it's a mutual disclosure
because if i turn towards if i turn
towards like no i really want to hear
your truth let's say
right yeah and even if it's the last
thing
i want i want to be true right
i want to hear it right and i want to
open up to it right
and there's uh
there's a sense there's a sense about
whatever that is
is that the truth is going to be good
because by virtue of it being the truth
right and me leaning
into that and becoming someone who would
be open to the last thing i want to hear
on some level by virtue of
it'll not only reveal more of the truth
but also
i'll end up being
mutually my character
i mean i think the character that i get
to become through
opening to the truth also
it creates character right
yeah right so there's this like oh the
thing that's difficult
it's like let's open that up let's press
that button right
because i know that that even if it's
not what i like right it's not what i
want
um there's a sense of moreness there's a
truth that
ultimately is something that i trust
yeah it it may not be the thing that
a part of me wants but i think
it happened to like you know
the self with the capital s most
people i think want that truth
but if there's a you know there's a
particular part that doesn't want it so
but i love what you said it's a very
mutual experience it's
not like i'm sitting there thinking i
know the truth
i never i i never feel like oh i know
the truth here
and i'm just gonna wait to reveal it
it's literally
a collaborative mutual experience that
we're all
in together and my clients may not know
that that's what it is it's not like i
made that part explicit but that's
what's happening
yeah it's like in in the process of
being together
it reveals itself and i'm just here to
book like to point at it you know but i
haven't
i haven't you know and then to help
people to
feel that truth in their body to like
you know i help
guide them but it's not like i'm sitting
there knowing the truth
at all but i name it when i see it when
it reveals itself
and and then it becomes like oh
you know we're all sitting sitting in it
and it there's a timing to it
and there's you know and yes there's
like deep
i have deep trust in that um
and i think circling for quite a while
has helped build that trust
because i've sat in circle upon circle
where
that's just you know there's been lots
of
evidence of that of like when the truth
is revealed
the impact that that has can only be
good
right i like i like the thing
that you said it seemed like it
revealed it more which was
it's not like i know the truth right
it's not like i know what's going to be
revealed it's more like
i've been able to attune to notice when
something's maybe
looks concealed right and then i'll
move towards that and go what's that
right
not like you know what that is but you
know that
it seems like if we move towards what's
most relevant
like the thing that's shining forth the
most the most uncomfortable or the most
simple
that if i if we open that up it's the
realm of the truth
right but it's not like you know exactly
what's going to happen when you press
that button in fact it's like precisely
what's kind of cool you don't know
what's going to happen
yeah but you know the request for
whatever's really on the other side of
that to come forward that that's the
thing
that you're inviting yeah exactly
exactly and uh
yeah so one other thing i wanted to say
about that
is people will often ask
you know how is it that you can sit
either in a circle
and get somebody's world for 45 minutes
or
do this work and not get completely
drained
and that is exactly how because
because i'm nourished by that
revealing and and the truth and that
process that we've been speaking about
it's life-giving so it never i never
feel depleted
like i really know
like i feel i could do this
you know there may be a time where i
where i need a break but
in general it is it is life-giving
to be sitting in that process of
being with what wants to be revealed
it's like there's an inexhaustibility
right
of nourishment just sitting in that
in that open place and being willing
yeah that's a really interesting thing
because like
it's it's interesting to ask ourselves
this question i just thought about like
people i just
remembered that were actually recording
sometimes i forgot about that
but i remember that and i thought to
myself god
be interesting if people heard what you
just said
and then thought about the places where
they feel
exhausted right
like where do they feel like that
they're bored or they're like
like depleted in what relationships and
what things
yeah and just start to like it as a
question to start to
inquire about well
it may not be that that thing is just
intrinsically boring it may be actually
that there's something
there's something concealed right
[Music]
or you're not necessarily listening
or tuning to the right part of it you
know
like your attention in a place of
uh that that's not that
you know exactly which is cool because
then you can then you're bringing
i always like it when i find out i'm
part of my own suffering right
like because if i'm not i'm
right like but if i'm the source of my
own suffering right if there's
like whenever i'm like not
i'm struggling with something and i
can't
when i when i see that it actually
it's actually the way i'm being with
something or the way i'm attending to
something or what i'm not seeing
right that's always good news for me
i don't know right but it's always a
good news for me
yeah it's in the realm of
uh i guess control
you know that you can control yourself
and how you attend to things and where
you put your attention
and that's about it and this is one of
the things about
i think what we're talking about with
circling and relationships in general
it is it's it's it really is a realm
that you can't control
like in in a very in a very real way
i'm not saying that people can obviously
people can manipulate other people
but when it really comes down to i think
at the deepest level
i for you to open up and
understand me right is really something
i can't do
for you right for me to
like receive what you're saying in a
genuine way
and really open to it like it's
something only i can do
like you can't reach into me and give me
the experience of understanding
right and it's uh i think that's the one
of the more frustrating things about
relationships is that like we actually
don't want people to be free
right we want people to like we want to
go
we want to make make them understand
this because then
but really when it comes down to it
there is
i think that there's some
phenomenologically
i can take i can like tie you up i can
like control all these things but how
you see
how you're experiencing what what it
means to you
about what i'm ultimately i don't have
direct control over it's like there
is a place where we're really free yeah
and so there's uh when you get down to
that level of intimacy
it's um that experience of feeling
understood and being understood
right or being honest and open and
having it be received
and and reciprocated
there really is a place where it's like
if i don't
if i don't want to be here right
i have to really want to be here like
i can't i can't make you
want to be here like there is a place
where it's not conceptual
there's a real there's a real being over
there
yeah there's also
there's also has to be
to be that intimate and to be that open
and vulnerable without the
assurance of being gotten or
understood because i cannot control you
in how you receive me
requires such a deep level of
vulnerability
but also like faith and trust
and value in in something bigger than we
have
say so over
um but in those moments
in those moments where where you feel
understood seen gotten
um those are like
those moments make it all worthy really
to have that kind of union and
like moment of ah like
i don't even know what that is it's not
even like um
it's not not feeling alone because some
people will report like oh i feel less
alone
yeah that's maybe it but that's not
quite it it's something
it's something more than that it's it's
um
i don't know what it is to be honest but
that feeling of being
joined or like seen or without having
had
any control over it and um
[Music]
is worth all of the vulnerability and
anxiety and
whatever else all the other sort of
hoops you have to go through to get
there
[Music]
i know what you need i i wanted i wanted
i know i think i know i think i know
what you mean and i know
it's this place where
it's more like there's the experience
for example of being seen
right like finally i mean we could talk
about that
what that is for a billion years like
that's fascinating
right about like what is what does it
mean to be seen
and like why is it so important and then
there's this place where
there's the quality that that just
happened
right that's
i could be deeply singing in that way
there's this other thing that there's
this other experience about it this kind
of open place
that i think you're pointing to which
i'm
i'm wondering if it has to do with i
think for me
there's something like something gets
restored about existence
it's almost like the sense of like that
that that was even possible
um allows me
to have a better be more open to the
universe that the universe allows that
to happen
that that's possible yeah
something like faith that's faith it's
faith
i think you're on to something i mean
it's almost like being seen by god
you know if you if you use such a a word
um it's like being seen in the face of
god or something like
that totally well speak speaking about
being seen in the face of god
is there this has been really great
yeah it has i hope people who listen to
this can
follow us and make sense of what we're
saying i think so
yeah yeah so so is
if they want to reach you because you're
you're actually seeing clients right
right now you're taking clients okay
i'm taking clients and i you know
teach relational courses and things like
that so if people
want to get a hold of me they can
contact me through my website which is
just kathy courtney.com
um maybe you can put that in the in the
link below
[Music]
and um i see both couples and
individuals and moms and daughters
and different types of relationships and
yeah i i'm happy to do you know a
consult for folks and
and have different ways that they can
engage with me
yeah okay all that in the show notes
yeah and it has been such a pleasure to
explore this conversation with you it's
been a while
love you i love you so much to take care
bye
you